Finding Aid for Camp Davis (University of Michigan) records 1874-1964
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Camp Davis (University of Michigan) records 1874-1964, 1910-1950
Camp Davis (University of Michigan)
5 linear feet
Summer engineering camp of the University of Michigan at Jackson Hole, Wyoming. Records include correspondence, annual reports, and other papers relating to the establishment and administration of the camp; includes papers of camp directors Joseph B. Davis and Clarence T. Johnson; also includes records of predecessor surveying camps, including the Bogardus Engineering Camp at Douglas Lake, Michigan; and photographs.
8731; Bimu; C367; 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
This record group was received in various accessions from the College of Engineering (donor no. 1884 ) and the Department of Civil and Environmental Engineering (donor no. 5375 ).
The record group is open to research..
The University of Michigan was the pioneer in the establishment and maintenance of a field camp for work in surveying practices and techniques. Organized by Professor Joseph B. Davis, the first session of what came to be called Camp Davis was held near Whitmore Lake during the summer of 1874. The next year, the camp moved to Thornapple Lake, and over the next thirty years, the site of the camp shifted about to a dozen different locations in Michigan's lower peninsula, usually near an expanse of water. This constant moving about created difficulties. Without a permanent facility, Davis and his staff had to move, assemble, and store the cumbersome equipment of the camp at the beginning and end of the summer session.
In 1908 Charles and Hannah Bogardus of Pellston, Michigan, donated 1400 acres of land on Douglas Lake in Cheboygan County to the University to be used as the permanent site for the surveying camp. Upon inspection Davis judged the land to be adequate for the teaching and practice of surveying, yet there were some problems that needed to be overcome. For one thing, since the lake acreage was covered with a dense growth of trees and brush, the area had to be cleared before any instruction could begin. Secondly, the surveying camp had to share use of the land with the University's Biological Station located one-quarter of a mile northeast of the surveying students. The proximity of the two groups with their different activities and their different attitudes toward the land created an inevitable tension which was to last for twenty years.
J.B. Davis administered the surveying camp for nearly forty years. In 1912, professor C.T. Johnston took over the administration of the camp. In 1916, the Board of Regents, in recognition of Davis' contribution to the University, formally changed the name of the camp to the Davis Engineering Camp.
In 1928, Johnston and some of his colleagues considered the possibility of moving the camp to the west. They found the site they were looking for in Wyoming. In 1929, the Regents of the University purchased an abandoned 120 acre ranch near Jackson's Hole, Wyoming for $2500. The location was ideal for several reasons. The temperature was stable; there were no insects to contend with; and the camp site was located near miles of open country with a varied topography most appropriate for surveying exercises. For over fifty years, Jackson's Hole continued as the home of Camp Davis; and scores of University students received their practical experience in civil engineering there.
The Camp Davis record group documents the summer camps for training students in the techniques of surveying and geodesy conducted by the College of Engineering's Department of Geodesy and Surveying. The bulk of the material concerns Camp Davis and Jackson Hole, Wyoming but also includes material relating to earlier camps at Douglas Lake and other sites in Michigan. The records are organized in five series: Histories; Michigan Engineering Camp, Early Sites, 1874-1912; Bogardus Engineering Camp, Douglas Lake, Michigan, 1906-1929; Camp Davis, Jackson, Wyoming Site, 1929-; and Photographs.
Subjects:
Bogardus Engineering Camp (University of Michigan); Davis, Joseph Baker, 1845-1920.; Douglas Lake (Mich.); Johnston, Clarence Thomas, 1872-1970.; Surveyors--Wyoming.; Surveyors--Michigan.; University of Michigan. College of Engineering.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Geodesy and Surveying.; University of Michigan. Summer Session.; Camp Davis (University of Michigan)
Subjects - Visual Material:
Alpena (Mich.)--1908.; Boats.; Camp Davis (University of Michigan); Douglas Lake (Mich.)--1908.; Glen Lake (Leelanau County, Mich.)--1908.; Mackinac Island (Mich.)--1908.; Surveying--Wyoming.; Surveying--Michigan.; Swimming.; University of Michigan. College of Engineering.; University of Michigan. Summer Session.; Wyoming.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Histories
  The first series, Histories, consists of a history of College of Engineering Department of Geodesy and Surveying, ca. 1930, and brief histories of Camp Davis including a published article.
  - History of Geodesty and Surveying circa 1930 (Box 1)
  - Histories of Camp Davis circa 1930, 1937 (Box 1)
- Michigan Engineering Camp, Early Sites 1874-1912
  Records of the Michigan Engineering Camps, Early Sites series include class lists 1874-1912, and correspondence of camp director J.B. Davis from 1905
  - Class Lists 1874-1912 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence (J.B. Davis) 1905 (Box 1)
- Bogardus Engineering Camp, Douglas Lake, Michigan 1906-1929
  The Bogardus Engineering Camp series is comprised of correspondence of J.B. Davis and papers relating to the acquisition of the Bogardus and other properties as well as annual reports on camp activities (filed with reports for Camp Davis).
  - Correspondence (J.B. Davis)
    - 1908 (Box 1)
    - January-March 1909 (Box 1)
    - April-June 1909 (Box 1)
    - July-September 1909 (Box 1)
    - October-December 1909 (Box 1)
    - 1910 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous 1909-1910 (Box 1)
  - Mortgage Papers and Deeds 1906-1909 (Box 1)
  - Land Contracts; Title 1909-1910 (Box 1)
  - Field Book 1908 (Box 1)
  - Acquisition of Bone and Allen Properties 1923-1926 (Box 1)
  - Suggestions to Homesteaders (J.B. Davis) 1908 (Box 1)
- Camp Davis, Jackson, Wyoming, 1929-
  The Camp Davis series provides the most detailed information on the administration of the surveying camps. The series includes files on the planning and cost of the Jackson Hole site, the instructional program and general correspondence. Overlapping the Douglas Lake and the Jackson, Wyoming series is a run of detailed annual reports for the years 1911-1942. Each report includes a discussion of the activities for the year interspersed with maps and photographs of camp life and surveying projects. In some cases, there are multiple copies of reports for a given year. These copies contain subtle differences in format and slightly different information.
  - Estimates of Cost and Plans of the Jackson, Wyoming Site 1928-1929 (Box 1)
  - Student Expenses 1931 (Box 1)
  - Inquiries 1933-1935 (Box 1)
  - University Lands for Instruction and Research 1930-1936 (Box 1)
  - Departmental Correspondence 1931-1938 (Box 1)
  - Reports of the Committees on Camp Davis 1938, 1949, 1953 (Box 1)
  - General Correspondence 1942-1964, 11 folders (Box 1)
  - Highway Group
    - Students Enrolled 1954-1958 (Box 1)
    - Announcements and Information 1950-1958 (Box 1)
    - Questionnaires 1954-1958, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Financial Papers 1953-1964, 9 folders (Box 1)
  - Newspaper Articles, Pamphlets 1953-1957 (Box 1)
  - Reports of Camp Davis Activities (Box 2)
    - 1911, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - 1912-1913, 1 volumes; 1 folders (Box 2)
    - 1914-1915 (Box 2)
    - 1914 (Box 2)
    - 1915 (Box 2)
    - 1916, 2 volumes (Box 2)
    - 1917, 2 volumes (Box 2)
    - 1918 (Box 2)
    - 1919, 2 volumes (Box 2)
    - 1920, 2 volumes (Box 2)
    - 1921, 2 volumes (Box 3)
    - 1922, 1 volumes; 1 folders (Box 3)
    - 1923 (Box 3)
    - 1924 (Box 3)
    - 1925 (Box 3)
    - 1926 (Box 3)
    - 1927 (Box 3)
    - 1928 (Box 3)
    - 1929 (Box 3)
    - 1930 (Box 3)
    - 1931 (Box 4)
    - 1932 (Box 4)
    - 1933 (Box 4)
    - 1934 (Box 4)
    - 1935 (Box 4)
    - 1936 (Box 4)
    - 1937 (Box 4)
    - 1938 (Box 4)
    - 1939 (Box 4)
    - 1940 (Box 4)
    - 1941 (Box 4)
    - 1942 (Box 4)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series consists of photographic prints, negatives, and two albums spanning the camp's history from 1875 to 1954. Photographs depict the camp's various locations and include staff, camp scenes, activities, and general scenery. A detailed item list of the 161 negatives is located in Box 5. Negatives which correspond to specific prints are followed on the item list by the folder number in which the print may be found. Negative sizes are 5x7" 6x8" and 8x10". The two albums, dating from 1908 and 1911, respectively, include images from Alpena, Douglas Lake, Glen Lake, and Mackinac Island.
  - Prints
    - 19th Century Surveying Camps 1870s, 1880s (Box 5)
      [1]
    - Camp Davis at Carp Lake 1890s (Box 5)
      [2]
    - Camp Davis at Douglas Lake 1900-1920s (Box 5)
      [3]
      (see also outsized UBImum/C367)
    - Construction, Camp Davis, Douglas Lake (Box 5)
      [4]
    - Construction, Camp Davis, Hoback River, Wyoming (Box 5)
      [5]
    - Grand Tetons, Yellowstone Park and Old Faithful 1933 (Box 5)
      [6]
    - Hoback River Scenes and Vegetation Surrounding Camp (Box 5)
      [7]
    - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
      [8]
    - Panoramic Views, Hoback River and Canyon (Box 5)
      [9]
    - "Scenery" (Box 5)
      [10]
    - Staff 1911-1923 (Box 5)
      [11]
    - Staff 1924-1934 (Box 5)
      [12]
    - Staff 1935-1942 (Box 5)
      [13]
    - Staff 1940s undated (Box 5)
      [14]
    - Staff 1950-1954 (Box 5)
      [15]
  - Negatives
    (The number at the beginning of each item description is its identifying number. The number in square brackets at the end of a line refers to the folder number in which a print of the item can be found. Not all negatives have prints.)
    - 5x7-inch negatives
      - Looking down Hoback Canyon, 1) (Box 5)
      - Looking toward Rangers' station, 2) (Box 5)
      - Head of stream supplying camp water, 3) (Box 5)
      - Looking northeasterly-Hoback Canyon, 4) (Box 5)
      - Looking towards canyon, 5) (Box 5)
      - Party group (Smith, De La Reza, Farrozas, Joumepin), 6) (Box 5)
      - Party group (Spoden, Sikso, Weber, Pierce), 7) (Box 5)
      - Party group (Schneider, Fan, Shia, Jenkins, McRay), 8) (Box 5)
      - Party group (Williams, Edmunds, Shelly, Bosworth), 9) (Box 5)
      - Mess and kitchen 07/05/1929, 10) (Box 5)
      - View from mess and kitchen 07/03/1929, 11) (Box 5)
      - Shop floor (Prof. Young at saw) 07/03/1929, 12) (Box 5)
      - Floor of instrument room 07/03/1929, 13) (Box 5)
      - Floor of administration building 07/03/1929, 14) (Box 5)
      - Flume carrying small stream over pipeline ditch 07/03/1929, 15) (Box 5)
      - Faculty bath house under construction 07/03/1929, 16) (Box 5)
      - Typical steel building under construction, 17) (Box 5)
      - Construction of typical steel building, 18) (Box 5)
      - Northwest view of camp 07/03/1929, 19) (Box 5)
      - Southeast view of camp 07/03/1929, 20) (Box 5)
      - Faculty bath house under construction, 21) (Box 5)
      - Digging hole for septic tank 07/03/1929, 22) (Box 5)
      - Source of camp water supply, 23) (Box 5)
      - Laying floor in kitchen 07/03/1929, 24) (Box 5)
      - Mess hall from southwest 07/04/1929, 25) (Box 5)
      - Putting steel on west side of mess hall, 26) (Box 5)
      - Mess hall 07/03/1929, 27) (Box 5)
      - Camp from southwest, 28) (Box 5)
        [5
      - Mess hall, 29) (Box 5)
      - Panorama from hill west of Willow Creek, 30) (Box 5)
      - Panorama from hill west of Willow Creek, 31) (Box 5)
      - Panorama from hill west of Willow Creek, 32) (Box 5)
      - Panorama southwest of camp, 33) (Box 5)
      - Panorama southwest of camp, 34) (Box 5)
      - Panorama southwest of camp, 35) (Box 5)
      - Drain of camp water supply, no. 1, 36) (Box 5)
      - Drain of camp water supply, no. 2, 37) (Box 5)
      - View from west of Willow Creek, 38) (Box 5)
        7]
      - View from Willow Creek valley, 39) (Box 5)
      - Looking up Willow Creek Valley, 40-41) (Box 5)
      - Prof. Young's washing machine, 42) (Box 5)
      - View from E'ly up the Hoback Canyon, 43) (Box 5)
      - View down camp road, 44) (Box 5)
      - View up the Hoback, 45) (Box 5)
      - Duplicate of no. 44, 46) (Box 5)
        [17]
      - Hoback Canyon, 47) (Box 5)
      - Hoback River, 48) (Box 5)
      - Hoback River and Canyon, 49) (Box 5)
      - Hoback Canyon, looking downstream, 50) (Box 5)
      - Mouth of Hoback Canyon, 51-) (Box 5)
      - Hoback Canyon, 52) (Box 5)
      - Looking down Hoback Canyon westerly, 53) (Box 5)
    - 8x10-inch negatives
      - Crook in road, 54) (Box 5)
      - Camp Davis 1940s, 1950s, 5 negatives; 55a-e) (Box 5)
      - Camp Davis 3 negatives, 56a-c) (Box 5)
      - mountain top, 57) (Box 5)
      - Hoback Road and River (car in foreground), 58) (Box 5)
      - High cliff, 59) (Box 5)
      - River to canyon, 60) (Box 5)
      - Road and river to canyon, 61) (Box 5)
      - River road to canyon and camp, 62) (Box 5)
      - Hoback near V-V Ranch, 63) (Box 5)
      - Valley fence in foreground, 64) (Box 5)
      - Canyon (view from east of camp), 65) (Box 5)
      - Beaver Mountain, 66) (Box 5)
      - Looking toward gate and camp creek, 67) (Box 5)
      - Woods Lodge pale pine, 68) (Box 5)
      - Camp water supply intake, 69) (Box 5)
      - Woods, 70) (Box 5)
      - Woods and Ant Hill, 71) (Box 5)
      - Looking towards canyon from east side of camp, 72) (Box 5)
      - Staff 1929, 73) (Box 5)
        [112]
      - Yellowstone Falls, 74) (Box 5)
      - Yellowstone Canyon (below Lower Falls), 75) (Box 5)
      - Clouds and mountains, 76) (Box 5)
      - Clouds and mountains, 77) (Box 5)
      - Camp Davis, 78) (Box 5)
      - Camp Davis, 79) (Box 5)
      - Camp Davis (short focus), 80) (Box 5)
      - Camp Davis (from hill), 81) (Box 5)
      - Camp Davis, 82) (Box 5)
      - Camp Davis (valley scene), 83) (Box 5)
      - Hoback River and Mountain slopes, 84) (Box 5)
      - Hoback Canyon, 85) (Box 5)
      - Valley southeast of camp, 86) (Box 5)
      - View of camp looking easterly, 87) (Box 5)
      - Camp Davis, 88) (Box 5)
      - Camp Davis shelters (from path), 89) (Box 5)
      - Camp Davis, stone steps, 90) (Box 5)
      - Camp Davis, on axis, 91) (Box 5)
      - Group shot 1930, 92) (Box 5)
      - Group shot, 1930., 93) (Box 5)
      - [#94 discarded], 94) (Box 5)
        [Discarded]
      - [#95 discarded], 95) (Box 5)
      - 6x8-inch negatives (Box 5)
      - Hoback River in Canyon 1930, 96) (Box 5)
      - Camp Davis, log house and barn 07/18/1929, 97) (Box 5)
      - Camp Davis, camp mess 07/18/1929, 98) (Box 5)
      - Camp Davis, camp mess 07/18/1929, 99) (Box 5)
      - Camp Davis, camp mess 07/18/1929, 100) (Box 5)
      - Hoback Canyon, 101) (Box 5)
      - Camp panorama, 102) (Box 5)
      - Camp Davis, 103) (Box 5)
      - Camp Davis, view from south 07/18/1929, 104) (Box 5)
      - Camp Davis, camp mess from south 07/18/1929, 105) (Box 5)
      - Camp Davis, sunset from the camp 07/18/1929, 106) (Box 5)
      - Mountains northeast of camp 06/29/1930, 107) (Box 5)
      - Camp Davis, view of Hoback Valley 07/18/1929, 108) (Box 5)
      - Spring at Hoback 06/29/1930, 109) (Box 5)
      - Camp Davis 07/18/1929, 110) (Box 5)
      - View of camp 07/18/1929, 111) (Box 5)
      - Hoback River in Canyon, 112) (Box 5)
      - Camp Davis, Grand Teton with Mt. Owen-to right 07/30/1929, 113) (Box 5)
      - Hoback River in Canyon 07/30/1929, 114) (Box 5)
      - Hoback River in Canyon 07/30/1929, 115) (Box 5)
      - Road in Canyon, River and high mountains, 116) (Box 5)
      - Road, River and high cliff in canyon, 117) (Box 5)
      - Teton Range 07/30/1929, 118) (Box 5)
      - Teton Range 07/30/1929, 119) (Box 5)
      - Camp Davis 07/30/1929, 120) (Box 5)
      - Jenny Lake, looking west 07/30/1929, 121) (Box 5)
      - Jenny Lake, looking northwest, Mt. Moran in center, 122) (Box 5)
      - View of Camp Davis, north of Hoback River, 123) (Box 5)
      - Camp Davis 08/04/1929, 124) (Box 5)
      - Camp Davis 08/04/1929, 125) (Box 5)
      - Camp Davis group 08/04/1929, 126) (Box 5)
      - View of shop, instrument room, keeper's house 08/04/1929, 127) (Box 5)
      - View of keeper's house and mess 08/04/1929, 128) (Box 5)
      - "Old Faithful" geyser 08/10/1929, 129) (Box 5)
      - "Old Faithful" geyser 08/10/1929, 130) (Box 5)
      - "Old Faithful" geyser 08/10/1929, 131) (Box 5)
      - Camp Davis group (Mr. and Mrs. Owen in center) 08/18/1929, 132) (Box 5)
      - Camp Davis group (Mr. and Mrs. Oven in center) 08/18/1929, 133) (Box 5)
      - Camp Davis 08/18/1929, 134) (Box 5)
      - Hoback Valley, 135) (Box 5)
      - West part of camp, 136) (Box 5)
      - View of camp, 137) (Box 5)
      - View of camp, 138) (Box 5)
      - Camp Davis showing the Hoback Canyon, 139) (Box 5)
      - Camp Davis 08/18/1929, 140) (Box 5)
      - Hoback River 08/21/1929, 141) (Box 5)
      - Camp Davis 08/21/1929, 142) (Box 5)
      - Camp Davis, typical residence building 08/21/1929, 143) (Box 5)
      - Interior of residence building 08/21/1929, 144) (Box 5)
      - View of camp 08/21/1929, 145) (Box 5)
      - View of center of camp 08/21/1929, 146) (Box 5)
      - Interior view of mess, 147) (Box 5)
      - View of camp, 148) (Box 5)
      - View of camp, 149) (Box 5)
      - View of camp 08/21/1929, 150) (Box 5)
      - Camp Davis 08/21/1929, 151) (Box 5)
      - Camp Davis, waiting for the steel, 152) (Box 5)
      - Camp Davis, waiting for the steel, 153) (Box 5)
      - Hoback Valley in Canyon 06/29/1930, 154) (Box 5)
      - Hoback River 06/29/1930, 155) (Box 5)
      - Hoback River 07/14/1933, 156) (Box 5)
      - Snake River 07/18/1933, 157) (Box 5)
      - Camp Davis group 07/25/1933, 158) (Box 5)
      - "Old Faithful" 07/29/1933, 159) (Box 5)
      - Camp Davis 08/13/1933, 160) (Box 5)
      - Camp Davis, looking southeast, Aspens 08/13/1933, 161) (Box 5)
  - Albums
    - 1908 (Box 5)
      (includes Alpena, Mackinac Island, Glen Lake, boats, and surveying)
    - 1911 (Box 5)
      (includes surveying, swimming, boats, and Douglas Lake)
Related Material
Related material on Camp Davis can be found in the records of the University of Michigan Summer Session (Call no. 8732 Bimu C361 2) and the collection of Joseph B. Davis (Call no. 851126 Aa 2 UAm UA1). Additionally several maps and personal papers collections with photographs of Camp Davis are cataloged in MIRLYN. Scattered copies of the Camp Davis newspaper the Black Fly published between 1913 and 1922 are cataloged separately under printed works.